angu 5175 this is called the
5175 this is called the
outcast endowed with these five
qualities a lay follower orasa is an
outcast of a lay follower a stain of a
lay follower number one he does not have
faith in the Buddha and the S he's unver
virtuous he is superstitious and
believes in auspicious signs and not in
action he seeks a b that's a big one
that's the one I want to speak about as
well he seeks outside the sunger for a
person worthy of offerings and he first
does does mous Deeds there POS so
possessing these five qualities a lay
follower is a stain of a lay follower so
in particularly number three he is
suspicious superstitious and he believes
in all suspicious signs not in action
Karma and that's kind of well most
people really to different degrees
yes because how many Buddhists believe
in
chanting even even if it's not these uh
kind of
rituals and uh ritual practices even if
it's your own
virtue if you don't understand the root
of your action or restraint in regard to
your virtue you are implying you're
believing implicitly that abstaining
from certain behavior and cultivating
certain other Behavior will magically
purify your mind will result in the
purification of your mind you don't see
how you don't understand and you
certainly have no direct input and
that's already superstitious view that's
already Sil
paramas even if there are no external as
I said crude ritual ritualistic
behaviors and and and and worships and
and and beliefs and and so on just not
understanding the roots of your actions
your own your own precepts your own
virtue will not be will be a fatter will
be silat parasa now obviously you
abandon silat parasa not by abandoning
virtue but by abandoning your view in
regard to it view being I expect this
set of norms and behaviors to purify the
mind for
me so understanding action is what most
people don't
basically that's pretty much and even
even all the like the the religious
teachers back in the day they didn't
they overlooked
it and they sought Enlightenment here
and there and in these practices and in
extreme commitment to to the to the
practice and endurance and everything
else and they missed what was right in
front of their
noses the root of karma it's right here
right now it's your own
intentions this Discerning that as the
basis for
practice and then aligning your behavior
by Body speech and mind with that
discernment that's the way
out so by doing acts
which result in craving well that are
from craving that result in suffering
Yeah by abstaining from those
acts so that you can understand the the
root of
action because certain acts inevitably
carry greed diversion delusion and and
and and and cause greed aversion
delusion to
increase so once the Buddha recognized
that he abstained from those
acts by Body speech and mentally he was
not entertaining them he was not
indulging them and then when the Mind dried up
them and then when the Mind dried up
from that he
understood my behavior is as pure as it
can be
now but it's still bound with action
it's still bound with intention it's
still bound with him doing that so then
he started looking further within the
same practice obviously not
elsewhere and what did he discover well
he discovered that the root of the
wholesome actions is fundamentally
actions is fundamentally
subjected to anicha and duka because of
its impermanence because of its unknown
ability so the mind now having been
dried up from greed of version delusion
left with whome intentions wholesome
actions understood that those cannot be
owned even if you want
to so sabar sabar for that very reason
and that then results in the experience
of
Sab understanding that these acts even
the previous
acts that you have abandoned because
they were clouding your your perspective
narrowing perspective even more they do
all share the same nature good and bad
fundamentally unable subject to
distruction destruction
impermanent cannot be
yours and that was the way
out so it's like the most direct way
there is no there is no
um there is no uh a middleman so to
speak between your practice if done
rightly and insight and results of it
that even if sayana who still not in
still has work to do when he attend to
things rightly withar and his Right View
he sees nibana he sees exactly what
nibana is he knows exactly how to get
there but of course now he has to keep
walking there and protecting that and
and cultivating that behavior
sufficiently until it's fully developed
but he has no doubt as to where the
problem is and where the solution is so
that's why he's Beyond silat paramas
he's free he cannot be superstitious
even if he wants to because that already
requires an external agent of chance
circumstance magic
whatever and that's not where the
problem was which is not where the
solution can come from either
so you you are
responsible for your suffering there not
something else that's that's making you
suffer that's that's now that you have
to appeal to to Grant you freedom from
it yeah well you could you could look at
it like that you could look at it even
in like
say even
if even in a in a subtler manner say say
you recognize that your mind is not in
your control that your mind is a wild animal
control that your mind is a wild animal
that's every now and then subjecting you
to suffering through its own like
thoughts and and refusal to listen to
you and so on so how do you go about it
do you roll up your sleeve take the
whip leash that animal and you start the
training or do you go and bow to the
shrine and chant and do all these
practices hoping that that will calm the
mind which then in return won't bother
you
it boils down to
that or going to
retreat protected environment enter a
peaceful State and then hope it will
last hopefully this mind will not turn
against me when I get out of the retreat
and when Life Starts hitting me again
but either way there is no direct
communication between you and your mind
and there's certainly no understanding
as to
direct understanding as to what calms
this mind and what agitates it there is
only the approximations hope and wishful
thinking so as you say you're not going
to be able to
see uh Sab dama anata all things are not my
uh Sab dama anata all things are not my
own
myself if you don't cultivate the
wholesome if you're not with drawn
thoroughly from the UN wholesome
withdrawn from the unome yeah un
wholesome intentions and actions by Body
speech and mind because there is that
that that Sut and some people get
confused about it it says I am the owner
of my actions yes so some people say I
am not the owner of the body the
feelings the perceptions the intentions
if you're an Arun you're not but the I
am the owner of my yeah because you
start as a non- arant so the only way to
become an arant is to first take
responsibility and ownership of that
which you assume assume the ownership of
you can't just be a
PJ still very much assuming ownership of
things and then just learn the
information that Arun is not the owner
of his actions because he's an Arun and
he's freed from his Aggregates and so on
and then just start applying that
information to
you it's like applying Theory to the
practice that you haven't developed but
saying that it applies to you because
well because of wishful thinking because
of an excuse
it's like saying basically if you apply
yourself and train yourself you can be a
master Carpenter anybody can be a master
Carpenter that is the nature of human
situation allows Mastery of carpentry
for anyone thus I'm a master
Carpenter already no you can be POS that
doesn't mean you are yeah so first you
have to admit that you're not take the
ownership of your
non-mastery of carpentry or in the in
the more uh pertinent sense take the
ownership of your possessions because
you do assume them and that is your
starting point if you train rightly you
will relinquish it all and abandon it
and then the statement of freed from
everything free from the action not you
can't own the feelings all of that will
be true will be applicable to
you because it's funny if if you start
off with nothing is mine it's all not
mine even my actions it's all just the
body acting and choices being made it's
got nothing to do with me I'm not
responsible for anything what is the
result of that I not responsible for
what the
person is just going to do whatever yeah
it's it's basically that's that that
shows the limit as I said the limit of
logic uh it's it's a true statement in
an impersonal public logic sense
that you are not the owner of Your
Action but that is not who you are that
is not where your starting point is you
always your starting point is your
experience here and now your point of
view the public view the public Logic
the applicable theory is secondary to
your experience as such but people put
that first and their own experience
second that's why you you need to be
sort of gripped with a desire to be free
from suffering because that is always
personal that can never be public
information doesn't matter how much
people try to make it when suffering
touches you that's always felt
personally so if you does know this is
where it needs to be dealt with then all
this information of Aggregates are not
yours and we are already in Nana and all
of that you realize well that is a true
that is true only in a certain sense
because there is a difference between
the same information by the way say you
hear the information that Aggregates are
not yours but you have not been taming
your behavior by Body speech in mind you
did not make the effort you did not
develop right
endurance and you get the information it
will only have a certain depth that
information it can maybe inspire you uh
give you an excuse make you make you
feel light and you don't own anything
you relinquish everything but
fundamentally you are bound with your
ownership not through information or
lack of it you're bound through your own
with the ownership through your actions
actions infused with greed aversion
delusion that is what binds you to
owning things and being controlled by
them now imagine somebody who has
Stained their behavior by Body speech
and mind has not been giving into the
UNH wholesome intentions of greed
aversion delusion has been taming them
has been enduring them rightly he hears
the information the same
information the same same sentence same
logic same conclusion same rationale it
will land a lot
deeper and the depth of that is
something that the first person can
never understand unless he develops his
behavior by Body speech unless he goes
through the
training and that's what it's meant when
it says that dharm is beyond mere
reasoning see you could reason that yes
we are not the owners everything makes
sense and look everything is changing
and all of that but that's not the dama
although it sounds like the dama
although it's from the
sutas it's not the dhama cuz it lags
that depth dhama begins only after
certain depth and no no amount of your
logic and reasoning can show you that
depth before you commit to the practice
of purification with body speech and
mind and arrive at that depth
yourself and that's the difference in
the
nutshell so when it said that DH is
Beyond Reason does not mean the DH is a
mystical thing that sort of cannot be
thought of and stuff like that no it
means reason it's not
enough because the Buddha never
dismissed the reason quite the opposite
he goes and he says a wise man wishing
for his own welfare he goes and listens
to this teacher or that teacher he pund
he
reasons he tries to intellectually grasp
what is being said and whether it has
potential to lead to freedom from
suffering or
not um whether he blame wory whether he
encourages actions that are blame worthy
or not and all of that not all he
abandons the reason and he focuses on
the moment and he has astral projection
experience or something no he reasons
but once he has reasoned he also starts
doing the other
work and the reason that he the
reasoning that he had in the beginning
will then grow through his practice of
purifying his actions by Body by speech
by
mind and then eventually when he arrives
at the deeper understanding of the
nature of things sees for himself he
will see oh yeah reason was part of it
if I did not intellectually grasp what
needs to be done I would not have done
it and no amount of revolving around
logic would magically take you to that
depth because that depth is only
attainable through your own development
of purification by Body speech and
mind you'll be able to see it yourself
not just hear about it reason will then
basically um as I said acquire another
dimension let's put it that
way so now the reasoning is two
dimensional but you're not aware of it
cuz you are within those two
Dimensions but with the depth that's
developed through uh cultivation of
virtue gradual training there is a third
dimension being developed in regard to
the same information same
reason so you don't acquire new
reasoning you just realize A New
Perspective in regard to it which could
not have come on account of meale
reasoning and permutations of your
reason and that's something a Buddhist
scholar can never understand because he
has mastered the two
two-dimensional reasoning of Buddhist
information and everything adds up and
every reference adds to everything and
everything is known but he's mistaken
that for
understanding understanding that can
only be developed as I said
understanding the third I mentioned it
can only be developed on account of also
your behavior going in a certain
direction and taking that reason with
it and then in hset you could see the
difference between your reasoning
two-dimensional and
three-dimensional but for somebody who
is so gripped and confident and
dependent on two dimensional reasoning I
logic um any
um any
information like this would just going
to be will be just assimilated into the
two dimensional
reasoning and no actions will follow in
the right direction actions of sensory
strain right endurance and so on because
of the confidence of the two dimension
reasoning and that's no and that's no DH
will take place and that's why exactly
you have many people today phds in
Buddhism knowing everything sutas inside
out poly fluent can speak are not even s
Upon
Us by their own admission ch m